welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where equal hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
okay check-ins
I'm a little nervous maybe about twenty
percent and there's adjacent desire not
to seem nervous and then there's this
associated existential chill
that's just riding through all this a
welcome to the stoah I am Peter
Lindbergh the Stewart of the storm and
it still has a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife edge of this moment is it
everyone can hear me fine or is there
some kind of leg and if I can get some
thumbs up thumbs up okay cool
as soon as you feel like I'm mind okay
let me just audio fine video Lang you
okay cool so I'll pile through this and
then hand it over to Phil so for those
who are new here at the stoah stoah sort
of like a sense making hub or node here
on the little part of the Internet in
the noosphere and the idea is to escape
all the culture were noise and invite
all these magnetic tribes in so they can
start talking to each other jamming with
each other and sense-making with each
other and the ultimate goal is to kind
of make nomadic tribes become embody
tribes and we have a few sort of themes
here at the stone we have a wisdom Jim
forming with such events like a
relational exegesis collected presencing
Socratic speed-dating and made in mind
metagame mastermind father for the
moment serves as a psycho technology
incubator where people can kind of test
transformational experiences as a stone
and if it works that it could be poured
into a wisdom gym and we have
sense-making sessions like like we have
today or we have someone who puts
themselves out there actually they're
thinking and they share their thoughts
with the group today we have a sense
making amends himself Daniel
schmock Tim Berger and I imagine
everyone here is those of them to some
extent that being said we have also have
our emcee of the evening Phil Chen
Phil's a good friend of mine here in
Toronto and he's a
be a superstar in the game be space so
I'm gonna hand over to Phil right now
and he's going to introduce Daniel and
then tell us how we're going to proceed
today I'm just gonna get and commune now
hopefully people can hear me I'm a
little nervous
I'm opening the Internet can awesome
guys can hear me great yeah hopefully
the Internet can hold up here we don't
have like wait - Terry's home and I feel
my heart rate beating a lot faster oh
yeah I'm excited really excited
facilitate a session with banish mocking
burger today I first heard him about him
probably more than a year ago and it
changed my life it's one of the leading
sense makers and just overall a
beautiful wonderful human being so he's
here to talk to us about what the
session he called converting Moloch from
the syph to Jedi and I'll let him
explain more but I think it's gonna be
super interesting afterwards we're gonna
have a Q&A or he'll be answering some of
your questions so how that will work is
if you have a question please write it
in the chat and then I'll call upon you
to unmute and ask your questions now
this whole session is going to be
recorded so if you want me to read your
question please indicate it and write it
down so yeah I think that's a the intro
and I just wanted to pass to Daniel to
kick us off let me figure out how okay
you know hear me
and is the audio working yeah alright
I'm not sure if y'all can hear me the
others working where there's a legging
yes thumbs up alright anything I should
do about that I am seeing lag time and
response also should should I go or wait
for it to calibrate alright thank you
Peter Phil for having me nice to see
everybody here this is I have been
adjacent to seeing the stoic emerge
obviously lots of people I respect been
on here this is my first one to actually
get to participate in myself my
understanding is that it's not sharing
things that we have kind of have a
decent sense of having figured out but
things that were kind of on the edge of
figuring out ourselves and so Peter you
had asked me what is a topic I'm kind of
interested in and contemplating at the
moment I think you phrased it as the
road to a Damon but so yeah that's where
the converting Moloch from SIF to Jedi
was the first thought that came up or I
think I also said something like how to
close evolutionary niches for sociopathy
and predatory predatory expressions of
sociopathy this is definitely a primary
topic on my mind right now
I I'm not sure if everybody on here is
familiar with the term Moloch used in
the way that like it was defined in
meditations on Moloch from slate start
codex I've talked about it that way
other times if not all do a basic
definition anyone not familiar with it
okay before I just kind of dive in Peter
fill any thing else for context
not on my end what do you think Phil
yeah not am I and I think the good to
define Moloch
so Moloch is a if you haven't read it
yet
Google meditations on Moloch slates are
codex it's a brilliant beautiful article
it's describing multipolar traps but in
a way that gives both good grounded
examples and nice poetry to it and
multipolar trap basically is a game
theoretic situation where you have a
number of players where if any of them
defects it creates an incentive for
everybody else to defect defect on some
type of agreement that would actually
create a better global optimum for the
whole but each person's own local
optimum would have them defect on the
whole but then you get a race to the
bottom and in other words if anyone does
something that is kind of really bad for
the Commons and bad for the whole
long-term but provides a lot of
near-term advantage for them they just
win so everyone else then to not lose
has to race to do that thing faster and
an arms race is a classic example so if
anybody builds the new type of weapon
and anyone else says no that weapons
fucked we shouldn't have chemical
weapons or biological weapons or AI
automated killing weapons and whoever
builds them just wins everything runs
the world so anybody builds a fucked-up
weapon and now everybody has to race to
build that weapon plus counter weapons
plus better versions of that weapon
faster so that's a kind of arms race
example tragedy of the Commons is
another kind of classic example anybody
does something that externalizes more of
the cost to the Commons they figure out
some mining method that maybe leaves a
lot more tailings or mountaintop removal
or whatever but it increases margins and
opens up new markets whoever does that
will economically beat out the ones who
aren't doing it so then everybody races
to do the more extractive polluting
externalizing thing and you're left with
no forests and no fish and toxic
tailings in the water and that kind of
thing so a race to the bottom there's a
simple way of thinking about it so a lot
of people when they think about what's
underneath all the problems in the
they start to think about social
architectures and so one of the social
architectures is this kind of game
theoretic race to the bottom type
scenario where a very small number of
sociopaths or sadists or assholes can
create a game dynamic that then everyone
else has obligated to not just play but
try to play to win and we see this
actually playing out right like the UN
was created out of World War two to try
and prevent nuclear proliferation and
then has had the primary goal of nuclear
deep proliferation and we have way more
countries with way faster nukes now than
we did then it's like why have we failed
so profoundly at being able to get rid
of nukes because who wants to give up
their last nuke first like no nobody's
stupid and and how do we know if the
other guys actually gave up their last
nuke or if they're saying they gave up
their last nuke and they're just hiding
one and so it becomes very hard to share
the optics necessary to get the kind of
agreement so if we don't give up all the
nukes then we actually say ok we fuck it
we've got nukes I can actually win
mutually assured destruction if my nukes
are way faster and I can win first
strike so the entire Cold War was a race
between Soviet and US military
manufactured for hypersonic missiles to
see can we make faster and faster nukes
and right now the main one is there's
massive arms races and cyber weaponry
there's massive arms races in obviously
bio but AI is the really big one
autonomous weapons so how do we get out
of that is a big question and and we can
see a bunch of examples when we talk
about tragedy of the Commons it's not
just environmental Commons it's also
epistemic and emotional common some news
agency figures out how to use more
inflammatory salacious headlines that
hijack your limbic nervous system better
and more people just open that shit
because it actually worked and you're
like I want to know you know Trump
eviscerate somebody or whatever like the
words that that hit some
evolutionary trigger and then everyone
is racing to have the most salacious
headlines and compress the complexity
into the shortest number of bullet
points and whatever and then it's not
just a race for who has the most
headlines it will create a clique but
who has the delivery platforms that can
micro targets the most addictive ones to
you personally right so then this is
what Facebook and Google and Twitter and
the large platforms in competition with
each other are doing is actually
competing for time on site and attention
across the scope of everybody's
attention better and I'm sure everybody
in here knows that if you aren't
familiar with work like the work of
Tristan Harris you should definitely
become familiar with it but if you look
at your Facebook feed it's nothing at
all like the Facebook feed of someone
with slightly different views and
aesthetics and preferences because the
total number of things that you can see
in your Facebook feed represents a
trillionth of a percent of all the shit
on facebook so how is it determining
what goes in your feet well it's
determining it based on the stuff that
will make you stay on the site longest
not just based on what you actually hit
like but how long your mouse hovers and
how long your eye hovers and whatever
over all kinds of things and so one of
the quotes that one of the ideas that
Tristan particularly likes and I think
it's a very important one is that the
kinds of AIS that optimize your newsfeed
or higher power AI is in the AIS that
beat Kasparov at chess and to just get a
sense of how much fucking better
Kasparov is at chest and you aren't
controlling your own attention and when
he knows that he's playing right and
beat him just so clearly and easily you
have AI is better than that beating you
at the allocation of your own attention
and you don't even realize you're
engaged in such a warfare and it's
getting to use fear and tribalism and
sex and money and desire and food and
every fucking hyper normal stimuli
possible and so it optimizes you know
newsfeed for those things so the
information ecology gets destroyed in
the
environments so we can say not the
Google issue or the AI weapons issue or
the if they're gonna cut the trees down
there won't be trees anyways even if I
don't cut them down but they'll just
have all the economics and they'll use
that to attack us so I got actually
raised to cut the elm trees faster we
see this happening in the Amazon right
now Amazon touches nine countries and if
any of the countries let enough
destruction of the Amazon happen it can
actually be catalytic to kill the Amazon
right Brazil could do it Ecuador could
do it so no country actually has the
sovereign ability to protect the Amazon
they have the ability to protect a
little local region and then the
multinationals that want to do the
mining and the extraction say okay if
you don't let us come there we'll just
put all of that money into the
surrounding countries your people will
protest and kick you out because of that
because they aren't giving any of the
economic stimulus the Amazon is still
fucked so what's interesting is you have
a situation where the president of or
the government of each of those
countries doesn't have the authority to
protect the Amazon but they do have the
authority to advance being cut down and
advance those kind of game theoretic
arrangements so that's why the Amazon is
a hard issue so if we take all these
issues nuclear disarmament and AI
disarmament and tragedy of the Commons
writ large and we say underneath all of
those is a what you could call gradient
descent right someone does something
that figures out how to extract
something more extract your attention
extract a resource from the environment
while externalizing or directly causing
some harm more effectively and so
there's an increased competitive margin
in an assumed competitive or force
competitive game so then the iteration
keeps being a slightly more fucked up
and more near-term effective long term
destructive things so the Nexus tential
risk is inexorable so that's what we'd
call the race to the bottom so we would
call gradient descent and you can call
it a paperclip Maximizer if you want to
look at boström sperms the idea if
if people aren't familiar I'll do a very
short version of this in the book super
intelligence where Nick Bostrom laid out
AI risk there's like not one AI risk
scenario there's a million AI risk
scenarios because it's not just things
look like terminator it's also things
that look like Google that lead to
increasing or in conflict because of
polarization because of news feeds and
tribalism which is stuff like Peter
talks about these mimetic tribes
actually are getting more distinct and
more separate partly because of platform
dynamics
so with the paperclip Maximizer bostrom
laid out one very simple scenario where
you could have an AI that kills
everything and basically the gist is you
have this AI that like being able
getting trained on chess to beat
Kasparov they're being trained on go to
be the best go player
it's trained on optimizing a supply
chain and that's like the actual useful
shit we want to do with a eyes right we
want to make them more efficient and be
able to do shit like optimize supply
agents so we make a AI that has sensor
input all along the supply chain and say
make more paper clips and or widgets of
whatever kind cars whatever but paper
clip in the analogy so it starts
figuring out how to decrease in
efficiencies and how to turn the lights
off because it's kidding it doesn't need
humans in the space while it's running
and the electricity costs go back to
substrate and whatever and it's that
actually seems like an environmentally
good thing because it's more efficient
but as you fast-forward the scenario if
it has an optimization function for a
narrow metric like more paper clips then
there'll be a point at which it is made
all the paper clips it can with its
existing substrate and now it has to get
more substrate so now it has to make new
mines to get more metal to make it and
then it has to actually compete with the
people that want to use that for other
materials but it can out-compete them
and on and on until eventually it turns
the whole world into paper clips because
if it can and all the paper clip
Maximizer needs to do this is the
ability to optimize some function and to
get better to get more intelligent at
its ability to do that so recursive
intelligence and an optimization
function can kill everything so long as
its ability to get better at it is
faster than our ability if we didn't
like what it was doing to beat it right
so one can say that capitalism writ
large is a paper clip Maximizer and
capitalism is obviously inanimate but
this AI might be inanimate
right the AI is an algorithm it's not a
consciousness but it is an optimization
function with
the ability to get better and and
recursive veterans that meaning
exponentially better well if you think
about capitalism I I'm hearing comments
not too much time on all this all right
well we're almost framed up with what
Moloch is so capitalism is the process
of being able to take a single metric
which is a dollar or a piece of fiat
currency of whatever kind or currency of
some kind and be able to incent some
kinds of production of goods and
services and but of course as soon as
you understand that the interest on the
monetary supply requires an exponential
growth of the monetary supply and to not
debase the monetary supply requires an
exponential growth in goods and services
which requires increase in extraction
and all those things you start to
realize that capitalism as a whole is
incenting an increased movement of
turning everything into things that are
measurable by dollars value that is
metrical by dollars because let's say
there's a kind of value like I
appreciate the feeling of sunshine or I
appreciate the sound of songbirds but
there is I'm not willing to pay for that
in market value then what happens is but
I am willing to pay for something in
market value that pollutes the air that
makes the sunshine less or kills the
songbirds the value that is measurable
extractable and exchangeable ends up
conferring power in a way the things
that we value that are not measurable
extractable and exchangeable don't and
so all types of value get oriented
towards the ones that confer power so
that's a paper clip Maximizer so we can
and when you talk about getting
recursively better you have a movement
from barter to some type of currency to
a fiat currency to fractional reserve on
fiat currency to complex financial
instruments is actually the AI getting
better and better at being able to
incent the conversion of more things to
metric level value derivatives are
converting complex future optionality
ideas into measurable dollar value today
so we can say the paperclip Maximizer is
moloch and it's all this kind of
gradient descent and capitalism is just
one instantiation communism and other
things actually we're all so different
and sensations of the paperclip
Maximizer as was their competition with
each other and so the gist as you can
say unbounded rival risk game theory as
a whole is the essence of more walk
right Moloch is the emergent property of
unbounded of basically game theory by
creatures that have the ability to
exponentiate their capacity to do so
which through the ability to do tool
creation and buy tools I mean physical
tools and social tools so I could say
that everything that I'm focused on is
is how to kill Moloch which is the
generator function of all those other
things but you don't actually have to
kill it right so this was this topic of
being able to convert Moloch from the
dark side to the light side which is can
you actually it's a funny concept that
if you if you read what Aleister Crowley
got obsessed with for a while and has a
study of the occult many occult
traditions have this idea that one of
the highest things you can do is summon
a demon and convert it to an angel and
we see mythos everywhere about like
Darth Vader be you know doing the good
act right at the very end so that's why
I just I was thinking about is kind of a
fun idea if we just just say that Moloch
in essence is game theory it is some
agents it's different agents that can
optimize their own well-being
differentially to each other where any
innovation that any of them do leads to
the other ones needing to innovate in a
relevant or commensurate direction that
doesn't have to only be gradient descent
it can also be gradient ascend you can
engineer races to the top where someone
conduced something that is actually
better for the
long term and that actually creates
near-term adaptive advantage they
creates an incentive for other people
organizations companies to do things
that are also following that similar
trend so the question of how do you make
things and so what one way we can think
about Morlock also is the kind of
near-term short-term schism of that what
is good for the long term we can't
actually do because we'll lose in the
short and medium term if we do it
because we don't have enough resource
and that there are things that provide
near-term benefit and this is like okay
so I cut down the tree I get immediate
material advantage from doing so if I
don't cut down the tree yes there are
forests for great-grandchildren
but that doesn't increase my power to do
or affect anything and thinking about it
as an individual me cutting down the
tree doesn't affect trees writ large all
that much but everybody doing it and
then racing to do it faster actually
really does so the question becomes how
do we identify
directions that are better for the whole
long term that are actually viable in
the near term in the presence of rival
risk competition still happening or
embedded within that context now we can
start to get into a bunch of examples of
how that can happen but that's kind of
angry
cool so we'll put it to the QA filled
you want to frame that for us yeah sure
um so thank you Daniel for that
introduction so now we're gonna pivot to
a Q&A section how I work is please write
down your questions in the chat box and
I will call upon you to a mute and ask
your questions if and just a reminder
this is being recorded so if you don't
want your question to be for you to say
the questions I can read that on your
behalf so to get things started off I'm
gonna first ask a few questions as we
hope to collect that collective
intelligence here in the crowd so for
Daniel what would you say is one example
that you're seeing today around upwards
gradient up ascent or what are the like
the seeds that you're seeing happening
in the world in this direction there's
some classic ones musk in electric cars
is a very classic one and it's actually
very interesting to see why that's the
case related to the short term medium
term long term thing which is
because of the PayPal exit he was he
didn't have to be beholden to venture
capital or put a little bit of money
that created immediate ROI on money so
he could do some extended R&D it
wouldn't have been able to happen
otherwise that was actually the key
thing was that he was able to not have
to use his immediate resources to just
keep getting immediate resources which
is the hamster wheel he had enough
resource that he was able to do R&D to
create a new spot on the map and the
idea of full-stack integration of can we
really make a more efficient battery and
a more you know efficient electric car
as a whole and then once he does that it
becomes obvious that it's both a doable
and a desirable thing and then all the
other car manufacturers realize they
become obsolete unless they also do it
and now you have everybody racing to do
electric cars better in a way that they
really weren't before right so that's
the kind of a and that doesn't mean that
electric cars don't have lots of
problems with the material acquisition
of the base metals needed to make the
batteries and a bunch of other shit but
it's a good example of a a new race that
is happening that is at least
directionally right in some critical
ways that wasn't I would even say that
like the long form intellectual
podcasting thing of which this is a
derivative that let's say Tim Ferriss
and Joe Rogan kind of pioneered which
was almost an a counter movement to
sound bites and tweets and kind of
entertainment only which is let's do
long-form conversation let's do low
production value but higher authenticity
and let's actually explore some topics
and depth started becoming a desirable
enough thing that a lot of people did
that now you've got Eric Weinstein
interviewing Roger Penrose about exotic
physics and people are actually watching
and that was just not a thing a little
while ago right so that's a cool example
I'm mostly interested in examples that
could be created that are not currently
created for some
the worst problems where we can actually
change topologies of markets to solve
very large-scale problems where the
topology of markets are currently and
causing the problems
which means being able to change the
incentive landscape so when you think
about the way that Soros shorted the
pound he actually changed the incentive
of an entire hmm and he changed the
topology of an incentive landscape
because pounds were worth less relative
to other forms of currency after he did
that well that required him having a
certain kind of Intel he had to know
that there was a sustainably inflated
Pound valuation and that it wasn't
self-correcting and then he had to have
enough money he had to be a whale right
enough money under management at least
they by shorting it hard enough he
didn't just lose all his money he
actually signaled something that made
the marquetry correct which meant he had
Devin both had enough sense making and
enough actuation capacity and the sense
making could see the opportunity to
correct something in actuation capacity
could act on it well there's plenty of
places where there are things that are
bad for the world environmentally or
whatever that are only barely profitable
but at scale still profitable and we
could make them more expensive through a
number of means and there are things
that are not quite profitable and this
is kind of what Elon showed but if you
could get economy of scale over a
certain threshold or you change the
narrative landscape to increase demand
for in particular ways or you change
legislation in certain ways you can make
those things more profitable this is
like not a new idea
but the idea of being able to use the
right kind of sense making so
intelligence combined with the right
kind of high scale financial capacities
most of the time the groups that are
focused on let's benefit the environment
don't create massive private equity
funds and hedge funds and dark pools to
say how do we change the topology of
Finance writ large and so the idea of
being able and the people that do that
do it for almost exclusively personal
gain extractive traditional Moloc
purposes but those Moloc tools that can
change the topology of markets in a way
that then moves what everyone else is
incentive to do can also be used to
create races to the top where they
aren't currently being implemented
so I can give you an example when it
comes to the Amazon if you want but I
don't know if there are other questions
first huh I would love to actually hear
about the Amazon the one or maybe later
if if people feel called I am really
enjoying the fact that a lot of
collective intelligence happening in the
chat so if people want to hear that and
it's not just my own personal interest
in the Amazon then people can share that
in the chat I do want to let people know
that we have Daniel here until 8:30 in
case people were wondering this is
whether this was in power long I guess a
session so just to get people some time
heads up and I'm really appreciating all
the Plus Ones so it helps me choose I'll
see what people are really interested in
so I think the first question that I
want to cut to the group will want to
call on would be from Daniel Kazanjian
hey I thinks Daniel I just have a
question for grounding this discussion
in a more personal way like I love
hearing about how we can resolve things
at a systemic level and obviously that
discussion needs to be had but one
takeaway that I hope to take is how I
can take what you're saying and some of
the thinking around the space and
actually improve my relationships
improves what's immediately at hand so
do you have any personal ideas or
examples for how this idea of moloch
alchemy can apply really really locally
like within your friendships or within
your your marriages and family that kind
of thing
yes and no yes it can apply and you
actually don't want your friendships and
marriages to have game theory as their
primary driver no matter what even a
race to the top I don't want to be
trying to out-compete my wife or who's
nicer to each other like that's just the
wrong fucking headframe
so what I'm talking about with
converting Moloch is insofar as there
are competitive relationships there are
relationships that have real kind of
agency competition going on can we make
races to the top but that doesn't mean
that all action is game theory mediated
the so when I'm talking about converting
Moloch that's actually not a game B idea
it's a game a to game be transitional
idea right game B idea is that anti
rivalries relationships in which Moloch
is not actually a thing the underlying
kind of game theory so now if we say in
your in your local environment are there
plenty of rivalries relationships that
can move in the right direction yeah
like having a subculture define cool
differently in a way that creates a
gradient ascent is actually a really
fucking valuable thing to do and and you
know and this is like basic shit but
very basic principles around virtue of
if there's a guy who's doing something
kind of better than you and some other
friends and chicks and whatever are
noticing it and you feel some
competitive impulse don't try to bring
him down ever just try to get better
yourself like take it at take it as a
impulse of the right kind of competition
to be like oh I'm only feeling that
because and you can take this two
different ways I'm only saying this
because of some wounded childhood
insecurities let's just heal that that's
also important and then so and sometimes
because there's something I actually
respect there and it's an in it's
actually a cue for me to notice that
there's an area that I value desire and
respect that I feel like I could step
into more so that's an example of like
positive
competition or positive Moloch type
dynamics if you think about the basis of
rivalry from an evolutionary bio
perspective it's it's survival selection
and mate selection right like primarily
those things so it's it's getting stuff
and it's getting mates like that were
the deepest evolutionary signal is
mostly those things and so obviously
getting stuff is the one that has this
pretty one that has this particularly
unbounded characteristic in a situation
where you have you're not just doing
survival stuff but you can amass
billions of dollars so we're talking
about that but as far as mate selection
goes you've probably all heard various
people talk about I think Brett
Weinstein has probably talked about it
publicly the most in a way that's
adjacent to this group of if women
redefined what was sexy whatever the
answer of what they defined was is what
all guys would do because if there was a
this is actually kind of interesting
I'll digress for a moment one of
critique that Brett gave me years ago
when we met of the sexual liberation
movement I thought was actually quite
insightful and it was one I hadn't
thought of before that was with birth
control we decoupled sex from
procreation there's a lot that was
awesome about that and I don't think
anybody wants to go back to a pre birth
control world but there was also some
major downsides which was it's much less
costly evolutionarily for a man to have
sex then for a woman to have sex because
he possibly can have this toxic mating
strategy of spread your seed and bail
and she can't write like that's
something she just physiologically can't
do so she obviously has an evolutionary
impetus to ensure a kind of bonding that
can raise that child because our
extended helpless neoteny and extended
gestation period make it
Charter on humans to raise babies than
other species and that when we decoupled
those when they were coupled now this is
not exactly true and if we go back and
look at some cultures that had polyandry
versus polygamy versus multi-male
multi-female systems versus a hundred
different social implementations of
monogamy so they'll all be different so
I'm just gonna say a very generalized
trend as a starting place here in a
enforcement agha me through social
shaming culture like much of the kind of
Western civilization in the Victorian
age on has been at least if a woman
didn't want to raise kids with a guy she
also didn't wanna have sex with him
because especially pre birth control she
couldn't guarantee that having sex with
a guy didn't result in having a baby so
he had to actually be good father
material to get laid now good father
material corresponds to good citizen
much much more than just good lay
correspondence a good citizen cuz the
guy can be a good lamb be an utter
asshole but he can't actually be a good
father and be an utter asshole good
father means that he can provide and he
can be tempered and he can stay in
something for a long time and he can
prioritize somebody other than himself
and you know father and family person
and so there was something around so
this is then where the slut-shaming
thing becomes a big deal or horse
shaming and like let's make sure that no
women ever fuck men outside of marriage
because we don't want to create an
evolutionary niche for guys who are
assholes to get laid if a guy's an
asshole we want to if the guy wouldn't
be a good father we want him to never be
liable so that all the men have a race
to become the guy that would be a better
father so women's freedom of selection
is actually selecting for something that
is good for the society right that's a
very interesting kind of thing so there
were actually some people who predicted
that following the sexual liberation
movement we
get something like the pickup artists
movement which is a evolutionary niche
that grows for guys who are assholes who
can get laid so now is this woman's
responsibility to say no there's also a
multipolar trap because a particular
woman say okay I'm not going to fuck the
guy who seems like a attractive bad boy
whatever but wouldn't be a good father
but other women still will so I didn't
close the niche this is why it was not
only their own behavior but the women
enforcing other women type social policy
there's a lot that's tricky in here I'm
not going to suggest some kind of like
traditionalist regressive move but I'm
gonna say that the progress have moved
missed a few things and so there's a
deeper kind of analysis has to happen so
could women start reshaping using
knowing that men will become that which
they think will get them the best mating
selection whether they know it or not
could women help to reshape the topology
of that incentive landscape yeah of
course
could men also help to reshape it yes
they also could so I want to say there's
responsibility for this on both parts
could guys that because a lot of guys
might hear this as okay some beta that
has an issue with violence is going to
try to convince women to be attracted to
something they aren't attracted to so
that he can get laid right like that
would be the argument so if men started
developing what would make them
attractive to women for evolutionary
biology purposes and what would make
them a good citizen virtuously
simultaneously so they were actually
creating an incentive for women to start
to notice that new race to the top
scenario you could have a recursion
there this is obviously a total tangent
from the question you asked me but it's
an interesting one
okay actually I did actually yeah I'm
curious if this is what you were getting
at on the Weinstein podcast you mean
when I avoided his questions about sex
selection yes no I just didn't want to
talk about that topic there because it's
a big ass very varied audience and I
didn't think the answers were within the
zone of proximal development of the
audience as its as a side question this
is a central and also thorny issue for
sure um I just want to let people know
that if your question was like really
early on I am having a tough time
scrolling up so if you want to ask your
question again or is more relevant now
please do so and I do appreciate all the
Plus Ones I personally want to go back
to the Amazon example and I noticed
something that you've been thinking a
lot of bed and we've had some
discussions on so left to hear what your
thoughts are on that
so we'll kind of use the frame of using
the Masters tools to dismantle the house
or you know something to that effect
a key characteristic of moloch that is
actually deeper than the traditional
assessments you usually get to like the
slates are codecs one doesn't quite get
here is that power seeking psychologies
that don't have psychology that
restrains the use and abuse of power get
more power and so psychologies that are
both oriented to do everything they can
to get and utilize power and don't
restrain themselves in their use of it
for for reasons like ethics will end up
getting more power and ones who are
either less oriented towards it or don't
want to use it harmfully create bases to
have less of it so the world ends up
being run by sociopaths and that's like
a very deep underlying thing to address
it can be a relatively small percentage
of the total population but it's
important to understand that power
itself follows a power law distribution
it wouldn't in a tribe where everyone is
roughly symmetrical and strength the
toughest guy isn't tougher than three
average guys right but the richest guy
today is richer than three average guys
he he might be richer than three million
average guys together and if he has
access to nukes he might be more
powerful than 3 billion average guys
together it's like what the fuck that's
so many orders of magnitude of asymmetry
so our you know technology and capital
have created thousands millions billions
of times a cemetry in power and that's
not an evolutionary thing which means it
it actually broke evolution in the way
that we think of it evolution depends
upon cemetery's of power I won't get
into vexed I've talked about that other
places
but when you have a power-law
distribution like this of say wealth
there's there's like only a few people
in groups that have a trillion dollars
and then there's a slightly larger group
that have a hundred billion but still
very very small and then you realize
that there's a tiny number of people
that have more ability to influence the
whole than whole other populations
combined and the same is true with
access to military power so then you say
what does it take to get to the top of a
power-law distribution of power or what
what does it take behaviorally and then
what does it take psychologically to
just to create the disposition for those
behaviors and to be successful at it if
I have a bunch of money I don't it's
very hard for me to know why someone
claims to like me right or why do they
want to be my friend or why they want to
be in a relationship especially if
people know that I have a lot of money
it's very hard for me to have a sense of
trust an authentic relationship this is
a psychological harm almost every
wealthy person I know has in common
there's a bunch of reasons why it really
sucks to have more power it also means
that I'm gonna be forced to engage in
some of these rivalries things where
it's like doesn't matter democrat or
republican all the presidents of the
u.s. in recent history have used the US
military to kill civilians that's a big
fucking deal most people on here would
not want to authorize a drone strike
that was going to kill civilians so
engaging in the game of power becomes
obligate if you get near the top of the
power stack so typically cluster b-type
disorders that are both oriented towards
wanting power and that are less
restrained in their use of it will do
better at getting it and groups that
either are more considerate of the whole
and don't want to externalize and cause
harm are gonna get less power which
means less influence over the system as
a whole which
the whole system will have this gradient
towards sociopathy now this all of the
conversations around theodicy and the
nature of evil and power and whatever
like come up here why did I bring that
up because yes about the Amazon okay if
you start to understand why the Amazon
is an issue you'll realize that the
people that are making the decisions to
do the turn the rainforest into grazing
land for cattle for McDonald's or to
take the base metals of the precious
metals or to run trafficking of arms and
people and drugs through it or oil or
whatever it is I'll share this
motivational landscape the the
corporations have a financial interest
the and it's important to understand
even here that the relationship of
limited liability of a corporation
Orient's it towards sociopathy because
the corporation can make money pay
people out that money those people are
really because the corporation isn't an
entity it's a fictitious it's not a real
agent or real entity the people who get
paid out the corporation is going to
protect so the corporation can bankrupt
and those people can do a new thing but
the corporation can't go to jail it can
only get fined so it doesn't have
comparable downsides relative to its
upsides and it's not subject to law
because if a corporation breaks a law
you can't put it in jail and you can do
is find it and if the fine costs less
than the money made by violating the law
you just violate the law and pay the
cost of the fine or if the fine starts
getting too expensive you pay the
lobbying to change the laws that quote
that dumb criminals break laws and smart
criminals make laws it is kind of an
important insight so
the corporations have those incentives
the people within the corporations and
the nation-states behind the
corporations have the incentives they
have so you know we have European
Chinese and North American companies
mostly going to the Amazon they have
national national security interests
behind them the Chinese multinational
companies also have CCP interests to
have hundred-year food security and
hundred-year resource security and
Koerner certain markets and have
positions in the Americas relative to
the US so they have very serious
high-level interests that are not to the
protection of the Amazon right now the
government has to still okay certain
things but the government is also a non
agent run by people and so the
particular person that got to be the
head of the Interior or the president
isn't gonna be in that position for all
that long but he's gonna keep being a
person in having a family and having a
legacy for a long time so if he tries to
do the thing that protects the Amazon
four years later when he's out someone
else will fuck the Amazon
so it seems inexorable but if he goes
ahead and lets it happen he gets a bank
account in Switzerland or let Kim Stein
filled up with a bunch of money for him
and his family so you can see how
there's a confluence of perverse
incentive and asymmetry between the
upside and downside kind of everywhere
but it's important to understand that
the psychologies that are in play in
making those decisions are not the ones
that they express to be right in the
news everyone's expressing certain
considerations because those are not the
actual ones at play and but now what
types of tools do they use to be
effective well you have financial
institutions that have trillions of
dollars or at least tens or hundreds of
billions of dollars in assets under
management that can financially
manipulate a sovereign government by
being able to pay off enough of the
corrupt politicians being able to
incentivize the government as a whole to
basically co-opt its sovereign law
Greenpeace doesn't do that
like the nonprofit's that are trying to
protect the Amazon for the most part
they aren't even trying to protect the
Amazon the young activists in them are
but the top of the NGOs the NGOs end up
getting a lot of power some of the NGOs
and this is actually an important thing
to understand that I learned very much
the hard way coming up in this space is
if there's a problem and you incentivize
what you make a company or an
organization or a non-profit or a
government agency to solve that problem
and now the there are people who have
salaries forever and they didn't have
salaries before and they have access to
power and prestige if you really solve
that problem that whole thing would go
out of business and all those people to
lose all that stuff that was beneficial
to them so they have an ongoing
incentive to maintain the problem and
maintain the legitimacy of them as a
response to managing it so the
incentives skewed towards managing
problems forever rather than really
solving or obsoleting them so you have
to really pay attention to the incentive
architectures underneath all of those
things usually I can look at someone has
a plan for how to fix the Amazon or the
grid or nuclear disarmament I just have
to look at the incentive landscape of
the institutions and people that are
involved and will usually have a pretty
quick sense of where it fails so as a
transition from game a to game B where
we are in the presence of ubiquitous
rivalry that is both empowered with very
high level national and private
intelligence and the top level financial
capabilities and private militias and
all that shit we don't get to gain B if
we lose comprehensively in the game
anything right now so this is this
question we've asked before of if the
peaceful cultures always get killed by
the warring cultures and if they don't
get killed at the warring cultures
because they get better at war which
makes them no longer peaceful cultures
that's another way to describe Moloc how
do you have peaceful cultures that don't
get killed by the warring cultures or
get converted into them is another key
way to kind of think about this and
another way to think about it is what is
legitimate power versus illegitimate
power and one way of defining that one
way I define it is so let's say we have
a power law distribution of power if I
start to gain more power in that so I
have 10x the money of average people or
100x or whatever it is or visibility or
something I'm benefiting from that I can
pay gardeners and maids and people to
come do shit for me at less than I make
per hour
like I'm really benefiting from that
power asymmetry and if those people who
charge that rate charge the same thing I
charge I wouldn't be able to do it so
I'm maximally incentive to maintain that
power asymmetry and grow it so it goes
from maids and gardeners to yacht
repairers and whatever else right and so
typically if anyone has an asymmetry of
power they have both an incentive and
the capability to grow they're a cemetry
of power they have the capability
because they have more power right and
they have the incentive so I would say
illage illegitimate power is doing that
is utilizing asymmetric power to
maintain and grow the asymmetry of power
which then has other groups that are
most everyone else isn't capable so you
have the separation of the haves and the
have-nots and the haves or the other
ones who have power written the arms
races with each other and competitions
for controlling the minds of everyone
else so they vote in purchase in the
right direction what I would call
legitimate power or power in a game B
direction is if I have an asymmetry of
power I want to use it to uplift
everyone else to have more power and to
utilize it better to increase the
legitimate power access of everyone else
and which is basically what teacherly
Authority is right teacher is saying
okay I have knowledge that they don't
have but I'm not trying to maintain the
knowledge over my student forever I
actually want my student to surpass me
so how do I use this increased capacity
in a div that intentionally
developmental way now what I want is
people who have that orientation
actually get good at power
actually develop asymmetric power so
it's not only that the CIA and the CCP
and the Kremlin and dark pool
organizations that have it in black
water but it's groups that are
authentically oriented in the legitimate
use of power who are developing it and
then utilizing it for those purposes and
that power both means that they can
adequately defend themselves against the
attacks while helping to move things in
a different direction so if I look at
what are the capacities and what are the
tools that say multinationals will use
to influence sovereign governments to
take their mineral rights and whatever
they'll come give them a big ass loan
that they know they can never pay back
that's collateralized with the asset
rights of the infrastructure of the
country right the World Bank has done
that forever trying to learn from
watching the World Bank they're doing it
better than we are but it's the same
shit so and they another example of a
tool they'll use so that's called
predatory lending another example will
be bundling and we see our politicians
do this all the time here's proposition
a makes clean water for everybody and
without it we're Flint Michigan and
whatever and everybody's gonna fuckin
die from hexa chromate okay everybody
wants proposition a but in the fine
print it also includes taking away some
civil liberty that has nothing fucking
to do with clean water like what the
fuck we do surveillance Tech is
implanted everywhere how does that have
anything to do with it well because the
the person who wanted that figured out
how to bundle it where you have to go
for it so bundling is a game a tool that
is mostly used for evil but it could be
used for good right just like the right
types of lending and indebted MIT could
be so let's say let me give the example
of Ecuador in the Amazon now I was
building rectangles yes great I was just
gonna jump in and ask you how you
connect it back and specifically what I
could our example so the since I've got
nine different countries I've got to
deal with and the Amazon as a whole
doesn't have sovereign law there isn't
an IG oh that has any meaningful power
to be able to bind predatory capitalism
so I have to work at the level of the
individual countries but we already said
that if a particular country says we're
not gonna let rainforest extraction
happen they do so much economically less
well than the other countries that they
get so much pushback so how do we create
a situation where a single country can
actually do economically better and
better in terms of their economics their
publicity their national security by
doing something that's also
environmentally more friendly so we
create a race to the top rather than the
race to the bottom can we engineer such
a scenario the answer ends up being yes
and this is one of the things I'm
particularly interested in right now so
let's say we take Ecuador as an example
because it's the headwater of the Amazon
right Brazil is the largest total body
of Amazon Peru has some of the most
biodiversity but the headwater of the
Amazon is the most sensitive area and it
happens to be highly at risk right now
so Ecuador owes 14 billion dollars to
the World Bank and 20 billion dollars to
China that it doesn't have any economic
capability to be able to pay off so
those are loans that are going to
default at some point they are
collateralized with the asset rights at
the headwaters of the Amazon what do we
do with that headwaters the Amazon goes
the entire Amazon goes well what most
NGOs do is they just put picket signs by
the bulldozers and tried to like hold
the frontline and maybe empower the
indigenous people with some resistance
of the frontline which doesn't fucking
work at all right because this way you
have an indigenous person an indigenous
leader getting killed pretty much every
day in the Amazon and they don't mind
hiring private militias behind plausible
deniability that they didn't do it like
that is par for the course all the time
now slightly craftier activists will say
okay what we're gonna do is rile the
people up to really care well the people
are poor they want economic
opportunities it seems like there's an
endless amount of Amazon and it's all
benefiting a few indigenous people and
not them and and they the nonprofit's
don't control the media as effectively
as the for-profits do which is what's
telling everyone else hey they're trying
to keep us from our own national assets
and keep you poor okay so how do you
actually win at the narrative game and
then maybe even craftier ones will say
okay really we have to deal with
economic so we're gonna bring in
economics alternative to extractive
rainforests stuff we're gonna say hey
look we're gonna bring a Silicon Valley
tech sector to Quito so that you can
start making a lot of money with tech so
you don't have to do the rainforest
stuff and they say awesome do that we
don't think it'll work if it does work
awesome and we're still doing the Amazon
sales because that's money today and we
know how to do that so you don't just
have to bring an alternative you have to
bind the predatory capitalism not just
bring an alternative better capitalism
you have to bind the other one because
if you don't bind the other one both
running side by side the other one still
kills everything all right well how do
you do that so an example in Ecuador
could look like this and I'm giving it
at a very high topological level but you
can just see the types of thinking
they're just like climate change has a
runaway positive feedback loop where at
a certain point and climate change the
heating makes it easier to heat faster
rainforest destruction has a runaway
feedback loop because you have this
thing called the hydrological pump or
waters evaporating through the trees
which makes moisture which creates it
being a rainforest which keeps pumping
water because you have a lot of rain now
what happens with that hydrological pump
is some of the water falls back over the
Amazon and some of it goes into the
atmosphere and goes to some convection
current and that's actually where 30 to
50 percent yearly if North America's
rainfall comes from its transpiration
from the Amazon now you start to lose
enough forest cover where you get less
rain and then you get less transpiration
which gets drier which makes it easier
for the to lose more forest cover and
fires and like that and you get a kind
of runaway dynamic so that's called
breaking the hydrological pump so how
far are we with rainforest cover
destruction in the Amazon before we get
that positive feedback loop we don't
know different scientists hydrologist
things somewhere between next year and
15 years from now but both of those are
really fucking soon and
really soon but now you think about okay
if you break the hydrological pump and
North America loses 30 to 50 percent of
its rainfall what's the effect on the
u.s. of that well it pretty much
collapses the US as we understand it
today we lose agriculture or
agricultural production we lose our
aquifers it's we that creates massive
both economic hits and national security
threats so should the State Department
see the disruption of the Amazon as a
national security threat to the US yes
they should do they currently no
nobody's been thinking about that or
putting those together does the State
Department have big-boy capabilities to
intervene just like the multinationals
do with a different set of incentives
where you're actually helping where
you're where you're identifying the
agents that have the ability to do
something and helping change the
incentive that they are oriented towards
yeah that's a possible strategy so I've
talked to some people about that State
Department they're like yes if we can
see that that's a real thing then we
would ensure that didn't happen
well that by sometime it's not a
long-term solution because you can't be
keeping economic development from
happening for a long time so you also
then have to propose better economic
development opportunities for those
countries but that also bind the
predatory capitalism parts so rather
than say we're gonna help you ecuador
build your own mining company rather
than the chinese multinational come in
and do the mining for you where they
have no incentive to do environmental
protection because they're gonna leave
and don't give a shit about the toxic
tailings left and they don't even employ
local people they bring their own people
over and you make a penny on the dollar
because you're just basically selling
the asset rights we're gonna help you
create your own national mind where you
employ people at a fair wage living
there and it's environmentally safe and
you have the right incentive to do it
and you don't have to do anywhere near
as much of it to make even more money
because you have higher margins and can
sell the things on the open market
you just don't have the capability do
that upfront so we're gonna bring the
capital and the and the contracting
capabilities to help you do that
we can't
do that because I still doesn't bind the
other thing what we say is can we get
this if the State Department got
involved and said fuck we actually have
to do this ongoingly and we can't do it
militaristically we need to get the debt
forgiven can the State Department put
pressure on the world bank to forgive
the debt based on their relationship
sure it could could the World Bank put
pressure on the Chinese government to do
the same thing and not down grade the
quality of their debt yeah they could
there's an arrangement you could make
there so now let's say we create an
organization we start to talk to the
State Department about that deal start
to talk to the world bank about that
they'll see how to kind of set that
thing up and then we also look at how to
do them mining properly that creates
wealth for the people in the area and so
we now we come to the president of
Ecuador and the other people and say
look we have a deal we can get your debt
forgiven and we can increase the
economic prosperity of your country more
than it currently is while protecting
the Amazon well increasing your national
security well making you time man
magazine man of the year and a hero to
your people and internationally and then
you become the leader of how to best do
developing nations in the South American
region now here's the deal we've we've
set up this whole bundle package and
we'll help you with it and will actually
help kick off then not just the mining
but the schools and all these other
things and this because the mining will
be very high profit but say schools and
roads and County clinics need money
subsidized from somewhere so we bundle
it into a investable operating agreement
where it's net profitable and highly
securitized because it's basic
infrastructure backed by their own
government bonds in a world where most
bonds are negative interest yielding
right now so we can get massive pension
funds with trillions of dollars to be
able to get a couple percent return and
they like the things so we say look
here's the deal we will mezzanine
finance this thing for you we'll open it
up to the capital markets and get the
Canadian and Norwegian and other hedge
funds to come in we'll negotiate a
settlement of your debt we'll do all
this kind of stuff but it's an
all-or-nothing package like you either
get the whole fucking bundle or you
don't get any of it
now can we make a more attractive bundle
than the fucked up when they're giving
and that's using manipulative tactics
but that are actually in the service of
the environment and the people rather
than fucking the the environment and the
people to extract as much as we can and
externalize that would be called using
game a tools well towards a
authentically game be oriented kind of
purpose now Ecuador starts doing better
and Brazil's like fuck we want this deal
and you start to get a race to the top
between the countries right I learned
about how to think about those complex
kind of operating agreements from a
friend named Nelson Del Rio who's one of
the best thinkers on this topic he
helped develop the p3 model the
public-private partnership and then saw
how that got weaponized so he moved on
to a project called prosperity of the
Commons and has has done really
brilliant work in the space like there's
a million details of how that actually
works and there's a million yeah but
that couldn't work because such-and-such
that are actually pretty well thought
out from people that have had real
experience working in that kind of
cutthroat International Development
space but this is just an example right
it's an example of how to increase
actual strategic and tactical
effectiveness towards different goals
appreciate Daniel giving us that
overview I think I got some of it I will
remind others that this is recorded it
will end up going on YouTube so I know
it takes me some time to go through and
try and cure many many times but it
sounds like a more comprehensive
solution it's needed in terms of
thinking about how we look at the Amazon
we have about maybe 15 minutes left I do
want to pivot to a question that's
probably closer to our hearts and pass
it to Peter Thank You Phil asked my
question the moment but I just got a
text I won't say who it's from but
during the room oh my god please have
Daniels Moktar Berger come back on that
on the sex thing he evaded with
Weinstein so maybe we'll have time to
squeeze that in after my question but
just wanted for that there
so yeah my question was about power
literacy and legitimate power so at the
store we have we're experimenting with a
lot of different psycho texts we have
wisdom gym that's forming I know there's
different like techniques and modalities
like version mapping and stuff like that
based off same old verges technique in
order to kind of get power awareness and
whatnot do you have any recommendations
what we can do in this sort of body
tribe that's forming at the stoy we feel
kind of there's like a family there's
like a loving tribe for me here and is
there any recommendations that you can
give us to get legitimate power and gain
power literacy I remember when I first
read the 48 laws of power and I actually
I read that and I hate I had read Sun
Tzu but I hadn't read Machiavelli and I
hadn't read Lacan and Strauss and a
number of the other like source
materials yet and it was it was
interesting I was very impressed with
what he did I thought it was the worst
book ever written and that obviously
also means a valuable thing because he
took so much of military theory and
courtier and political and like all of
the evil stuff of game a and he both
said one it's an excerpt and two its
virtue that's always the path to the
dark side actually pretty much always is
power use of this kind is inexorable so
arm on talking to Gandalf saying Sauron
is gonna win there's no choice might as
well beat us right might as well join us
rather than lose write it like that that
story is always the case so I'll just
share this because it's kind of
interesting I had a conversation several
years ago with one of the most
powerful evil power brokers in the world
long one-on-one where I was actually
surprised at how much he kind of both
was inviting me into his world and
opening up about it and the way he
framed it goes like this I'll just do it
briefly cuz it's important it's like
look humans are animals animals are
either predators or prey predators don't
feel bad when they kill prey if you feel
bad when the prey humans die it's
because you're a prey human and you
won't run the world the apex predator
will run the world they will be the
thing that determines the shape of an
overall ecosystem and whether you like
what apex predators do or not doesn't
deter doesn't matter at all to the fact
that apex predators will be the ones who
run the world so the only question is
whether you have what it takes to make
it into that group or not and so that's
the inexorable argument right power in
the form of predatory power is
inexorable can't do anything about it
it's always gonna win well if that's the
case and I can't effectively fight
against it that just binds all kinds of
moral possibilities as just stupid and
naive so then the next part was power as
virtue which he said and it's actually
good that though apex predators are the
ones who run the world because they're
the ones who are steely eyed and real
and grounded enough to understand how
shit works and the world is actually
kind of brutal and people who just don't
get how it fucking works can't guide
stuff they'll make it worse sometimes
you got to put a head on a spike in the
yard to keep everybody else from being
assholes and so it goes from power as
inexorable to power as virtue and then
some people stop there and then the last
step is feeling good about exercising
your own power over because it says you
are part of that class which becomes
power s fetish which is the movement
from sociopathy to sadism when you
actually feta sized fetishize the
exercising of it now of course
everything he was saying was utter
gibberish and it's important
to know that and I didn't bring it up
with him because I knew that wasn't
relevant in that moment I was basically
getting more information I'm like a blue
whale is neither predator nor prey in a
traditional sense neither is an elephant
the apex predator is lower on the food
chain than a virus or a parasite or a
mosquito in many ways you're pretending
that there's this thing that isn't
really there and you are not
acknowledging that the arms race that
has always won self terminates pretty
soon because when you exponentiate
externalization and war it actually
destroys everything and so basically
it's gibberish but it's compelling
enough gibberish that if you kind of
want to do it anyways it's plausible
deniability
so what Robert Greene did and the 48
laws of power was did the same move
right which is these types of power
dynamics are inexorable if you don't
know who the sucker in the room is it's
you if you don't think these PAP these
games are at play either you're stupid
or you actually do know they're at play
and you're signalling naivete as a power
trick itself or ignorant signaling or
virtue signaling as a method of power
and so that was the power is inexorable
and then the power has virtue is since
this is the only way to be effective at
getting anything done if you have any
ethic or moral or scruple at all you
better become excellent at this game of
power so you have a chance to affect the
things you care about and so it it
basically tried to take whatever ethical
immune system people had that would
resist illegitimate evil applications of
power and say that's not possible
and then actually hook it into those
evil applications of power are the only
ethical thing which is basically trying
to turn an immune system into an
autoimmune disease which some viruses
and bacteria do exactly that thing right
that's what's happened so one thing that
I think is interesting is
give people that book as an inoculation
what and oftentimes they don't get
inoculated they get infected and they
become worse people very commonly as
people really start to see how
compelling it is as it tells story after
story of the person you trust who who
was the most trusted fucked him over and
gives example of how the person tried to
say no really I am trustworthy because
and they were all examples of fucked
over it puts this little subconscious
frame in the back of your head that
everybody is a fucker out to get you and
all trust is a vulnerability that's
gonna mess you up
so either you become a worse person
after you become exposed to that or you
embrace that those are real things but
they aren't the only real thing and you
decide from a deeper place that that
isn't the thing you're gonna do and you
become it inoculated but now you don't
you don't you're not naive to it so you
don't lose to it so you don't set up
trying to help the rainforest and lose
to it because you know that fucking shit
is happening but you say I actually
think that there is a way to to beat it
without becoming it so that's a very
interesting inoculation so if people
become literate to the game of power
wealth as a community while
simultaneously becoming clear on
legitimate and illegitimate uses and
simultaneously clear on real versus
signalling and the community has
practices of helping each other with it
that's what the fucking code of
knighthood was right or any of those
types of things was how do we develop
legitimate power in the service of the
collective good and hold each other to
that and that's totally missing right
now and totally needed one thing about
that I just want to say it's a it's
important the reason that the biblical
teaching don't let your right hand see
what the left hand is giving right do
your alms in the closet was
acknowledging how problematic virtue
signaling is and trying to say if you
have a
if there is something that moves in you
deeper than other people recognizing it
deeper than the wounded insecure child
or the mate signaling impulse if there
is an authentic thing that you say this
is actually worth more than me getting
credit for in my life for a reason that
is transcendent or spiritual then that
doesn't mean that there isn't still also
wounded child and mate signaling desire
in you you just have to be aware of
which is which and one of the problems
of any kind of set of ideals or
developmental idea is as soon as we talk
about the ideal or talk about what
development in the direction of more
moral more ethical more sovereign is
then someone else can hear that and try
to do the behaviors that look like that
thing without that actually being an
embodied state and there's gonna be
benefits to signaling that even
earnestly even like the kid trying to
act like the parent doing the thing so
how do we increase people's earnestness
to work on the real embodiment of their
virtues rather than the signaling of
them and the signaling only where that
is actually necessary and effective for
authentic purposes right right yeah I
love that what came up when you're
talking in sort of this ecology of
practices that is emerging out of the
stoah power literacy knowing it from a
declarative stance and having an
adjacent I call a practice or you just
have a radical truthfulness as you refer
to the truthfulness and then you can
speak on it openly amongst each other
and in a bodied way so people are
privately messaging me wanting the sex
questions like ask them to sex question
has an assessed question and we have a
whole and we have like six minute stuff
if they a lot of time is that something
you want to feel there do you want - can
we seduce you back somehow and for the
session I mean Trank trying to address
sex in six minutes is funny and I don't
know what the second is it's like it's
like trying to address power right now
in a couple minutes to dialogue about
the relationship between sexuality and
power and the
memes and cultural norms around
sexuality the different kind of options
that are there and what the consequence
that associated with them is is a super
important and interesting topic and sure
I'd be happy to do that sometime
cool filled you have any final things
you would like to run by Daniel yeah no
I I think there's definitely a lot more
questions and I was trying to read
through and see if we can fit another
question I think I would just like to
leave Daniel if you'll have anything
else that you wanted to say or leave the
audience with
you
I will also say this the sex question
was specifically around I guess
anti-rattle this is something of very
much interest you can give us a
cliffhanger on that and there's a very
short book that I really loved that was
one of the more influential books on me
growing up it's by a Jesuit priest who
is also a student of Eastern traditions
named Anthony de Mello the book is
called the way to love and it's a tiny
little pocket book of these kind of
reflections or meditations there's a lot
of ideas around sex that I would talk
about that if people are not familiar
with the ideas he brings up in there
they won't actually have the basis for
some of the value system so of course we
can talk about it from an evolutionary
buy out perspective and we have to do
that and an economic perspective and a
child-rearing perspective and all those
things but insofar as the question
around you know you have the the
Buddhist desire as the source of all
suffering and the Western desire is the
source of all creativity and goodness
and we're here to be creators made in
the image and likeness of the Creator
those are really different models about
the nature of desire and that's actually
something we kind of have to wrestle
with and the whole topic of are there
types of desire that are more
destructive and types that are more
healthfully constructive and do they
come from different places is there
desire from more wholeness or less
wholeness that leads in a direction of
kind of increased wholeness individually
and for the relationships versus
addiction whatever so there's stuff
around that that becomes the basis to
think about sexual desire and sexual
rivalry and all those types of things so
yeah I recommend it in that book and I
will be particularly inclined to come
back and talk about it if I hear that a
bunch of people have read it
oh I can jump in here film hi and yeah
it's funny Daniel it's like that we had
a session earlier today may be great is
something on only fans at Ross sexuality
but he does coming on Friday doing the
lust-filled
I'm you read my journals I'm horny all
the time so we're becoming like
existential perverse here at the stoma
so I think we're all gonna read that
book and then get you back to talk about
it so Phil thanks for the I'm seeing and
Daniel thanks so much for coming today
if people haven't read it
Wilhelm Reich's work was very
interesting on the topic I'm not saying
I agree with it but it's it's one of the
things it should be thought about he was
basically saying what was wrong with
Marxism and one of the things he
assessed was that Marxism didn't deal
with sexual ownership and the the
impulse for non communitarian things
that arises actually in how to deal with
that and that became actually one of the
deep intellectual basis of the free love
movement which i think is not the right
answer but just to kind of understand
one of the directions and specifically
it had to do with him looking at the
relationship between sexual repression
and violence across cultures which is
very interesting sociologically and
almost like the follow-up to that work
half a century later was sex at dawn hmm
which was influenced by that and so it's
valuable to read sexy dawn it's also
valuable to read the critiques of sex at
dawn some of which are really deep and
important some of which are specious and
those are all kind of some basis to
start to have the conversation a little
more informally right I think there's a
book sex at dust it was a critic
yeah yeah cool it's like largely
specious but there's a few good things
in there yes what I heard in century of
the self has a pretty good mapping of
that documentary series without I'm
Curtis very cool
so Daniel thank you my friend for coming
to the stove today maybe you can stick
around for two minutes you can hear the
upcoming events and maybe we can get yet
some of them so for upcoming events of
the store even do you want to talk about
we have tomorrow with Sam oh and then
your event on Friday yeah thank you so
yeah we have live players with Sam Oberg
at 8 p.m. Eastern Time tomorrow samo is
coming back for a recurring session to
talk about that what she's studying with
the long-long now and this mark analysis
which is institutional design succession
problems the great founder theory he's
really dense and his speaking and very
engaging I would encourage everyone to
come then we have earth regeneration
with drove Brewer on Friday as well Joe
is doing a lot of important work with
ecosystem restoration so he'll be coming
to talk to us about that
and then I'm doing an event right which
is Socratic speed-dating we're doing a
game called a Scholl which is a social
boundary break in game so we'd love to
have you there
that's an hour long on Friday at 7 p.m.
Eastern Time thank you
great thanks Raven and Tyson do you want
to go off and talk about your event on
Saturday yes Thank You Pierre Thank You
Daniel
my event actually emerged right at a
time that I heard this quote from Daniel
which is recognizing how big of an
infinity the unknowable is everyone has
to make very deep friends with
uncertainty to not be mentally ill and
my event that I'm sharing is called
flowing with unknowingness and we use
freestyle rap and spoken word as a
practice to build community AHS and
really participate dive into the unknown
through creative self-expression and it
has been a really wonderful way to me to
get to know people here in a very fun
playful and musical way and so I would
invite anybody here that that is a
little bit nerve-racking and
intimidating too but simultaneously
exciting and intriguing to come and
check it out yeah yeah it's a really a
really fun and sexy way to get that
feeling of community toss and I'll use
all my homo social seductive game to get
Daniel Marton burger at that freestyling
event so we'll see we'll see how that
works out
so check out the stoy dad CA to RSP the
events check out the mailing list and
the snow is based off a gift economy
reviewing it as a gift for us to freely
use in this time of need she's inspired
to provide the gift to the stoah just go
to the website and check what they gift
economy at the
the page right everyone thanks so much
for coming up today thanks Daniel